Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Filippo Tommaso Marinetti papers
1888-1983
1888-1944
GEN MSS 130
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
27.5
(57 boxes)
The Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, printed items, diaries and memorabilia documenting and relating to the work of Marinetti and to the Futurist art movement.
Marinetti, F. T., 1876-1944
Marinetti Cappa, Benedetta, 1897-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Marinetti Family, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 57: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
FILIPPO TOMMASO MARINETTI (1876-1944)
Filippo Tommaso Marinetti (1876-1944), Italian writer, founder of Futurism and its leader.
Scope and Contents
The Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, printed items, diaries and memorabilia documenting and relating to the work of Marinetti and to the Futurist art movement.
Organized into ten series: I. Letters by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1909-1944. II. Letters by Benedetta Cappa Marinetti, 1921-1944. III. Letters to and about Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1989-1970. IV. Writings by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1895-1944. V. Writings of Others, 1900-1961. VI. Manifestos [cataloged separately]. VII. Catalogues [cataloged separately]. VIII. Photographs, 1888-1944. IX. Clippings, 1914-1983. X. Special Files, 1918-1940.
Arts, Modern -- 20th Century; Authors, Italian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Futurism (Art); Futurism (Literary movement) -- Sources; Italian literature -- 20th Century; Diaries; Photographic prints; Marinetti Cappa, Benedetta, 1897-1977; Marinetti, F. T., 1876-1944
- Letters by FILIPPO TOMMASO MARINETTI, 1909-1944; Series I; 2; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Unless otherwise indicated, all letters are ALS (autograph letter signed).
  - Unidentified Recipients
    - n.d. Scusate il mio silenzio... 4 p. AL; n.d. Volevo fermarmi... 4 p. AL; n.d. Excusez le retard... 1 p. incomplete and in the hand of BCM; [1909] Excusez-moi d'avoir... 5 p.; [1909 or 1910] La ringrazio anzitutto... 18 p. and 4 p. of notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armani [& Stein, Rome]
    - 1915 Mar 19 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Belli, Piero
    - [No year] Aug 26 2 p. in the hand of BCM, corrected, dated and signed by FTM (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boissy, Gabriel
    - [1932? Dec?] 7 p. AL (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cafaro, Gaetano
    - 1936 Jul 19 1 p. TL; on the verso in the hand of FTM: "Cafaro Editore Lecce" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Casini, Giorgio
    - n.d. Ho riletto tutte... Postcard; n.d. Grazie, Auguri... Postcard; 1931? 21 Mandatemi... Postcard (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clerici, Ala Marinetti
    - 1932 Nov ?9 Postcard; 1935 Oct 31 Telegram (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Corradini, Bruno (Corra, Bruno, pseud.)
    - 1918 Mar 20 Sono lieto di mettere... 1 p. With envelope; 1918 Mar 20 Lieto di mettere... 1 p. labelled "L'Isola dei baci" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marinetti, Benedetta Cappa
    [Filed after Rougena Zátkova, below]
  - Mezzasoma, Fernando
    - 1944 May 22 1 p. Upper right corner missing (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mussolini, Benito
    - 1943 Oct 18 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notari, Umberto
    - n.d. Rispondo con vivo piacere... 6 p. AL (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Paris-Soir?]
    - [1924?] Nel tuo autorevole... 4 p. In hand of BCM with corrections by FTM (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Piazzoni, Vittoria Marinetti
    - [1935] Oct 23 Signed also "Mammina" Postcard; 1935 Oct 30 Telegram; [1935 Nov 13] Addressed also to Ala and Luce Marinetti Postcard; 1938 Jul 1 Signed also by Luigi Bonelli, G. Francesco Malipiero, and Sangrigi? Postcard; [1938? Aug] Addressed also to Ala Marinetti 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [La Revue Bleue?]
    - n.d. Je me hâte de vous exprimer... 8 p. AL (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vielé-Griffin, Francis
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Series V, Box 48, folder 1933
  - Viggiani, N.
    - 1926 Mar 11 2 p. AL in the hand of BCM (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Zátkova, Rougena
    - n.d. Ieri sera (seconda)... 1 p.; n.d. Ho parlato molto di voi... 1 p.; n.d. Ho parlato ancora... 2 p.; No year Apr 1 3 p. In hand of BCM signed by FTM and BCM; [1921 Feb 5?] 2 p. Enclosed: a letter from BCM; 1921 Feb 17 4 p. In hand of BCM, signed Filippo Tommaso Marinetti (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - [1921 Feb 22] 2 p.; 1921 Oct 26 1 p. Telegram; [1922 Mar 27] 2 p.; [1922 Mar 28] 2 p.; 1922 May 3 Envelope only; [1922? May 22] Grazie per la vostra... 1 p. Ho parlato di voi... 1 p. Both in the same envelope with newspaper clipping from Il Mondo 1922 Apr 20
    - [1922] May 22 L'esposizione sarà... 1 p. In hand of BCM; [1922 Jun 1] 2 p. Enclosed: clipping dated 1922 Apr 13; ALS on a card of the Sottosegretario di Stato per le Belle Arti dated Rome 1921 Apr 6, with an unidentified signature 1922 Jun 17, envelope only
  - Marinetti, Benedetta Cappa
    Boxes 2-9 contain letters, mostly undated, from Marinetti to his wife Benedetta. The letters are in the order in which BCM preserved them
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - n.d. Tanti tanti baci tenerissimi... 1 p.; n.d. Tanti tanti baci alla... 1 p.; n.d. alla cara grande... 1 p.; n.d. Ti piace questo... 1 p.; n.d. ho parlato ora con... 4 p.; n.d. ho telefonato... 4 p. AL; n.d. Baci Marinetti... 1 p. Telegram
    - n.d. Ricevo tuo telegramma... 1 p.; n.d. Con tutto il cuore... 1 p. Telegram; n.d. ti mando tanti... 2 p.; n.d. ti penso sempre... 1 p.; n.d. dolce passione ho ricevuto... 1 p.; n.d. Algeri... Postcard; n.d. Bacio teneramente... 1 p. Telegram Feb 3 Spero arrivare... 1 p. Telegram
    - Mar 17 Verro oggi... 1 p. Telegram Oct 1 Sarò domani... 1 p. Telegram Oct 14 Oggi 14 Ottobre... 1 p. Dec 20 Telegrafami... 1 p. Telegram
    - 1918-19 May 27 Labelled by BCM: 1918 1919 fino 27 maggio" (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - n.d. Con profonda simpatia... 1 p.; n.d. Desidero salutarvi... 2 p.; [1918] Vi chiamo cosi perchè... 2 p. Probably 1918 because FTM gives army address on verso of p. 2; [1918] Ho letto una seconda volta... 2 p. army address; [1918] Jun 15 2 p.; [1918 Sep 6] 2 p.
    - [1919 Jan 16] 2 p.; [1919 Feb 7] 1 p.; 1919 Feb 14 1 p. Telegram; [1919 Feb 18] 1 p.; 1919 Feb 19 1 p. Telegram; [1919 Feb 19] 2 p. Enclosed: draft of a poem by and in the hand of BCM (identified by LMB); [1919 Feb 28] 1 p.
    - [1919 Mar 3] 1 p. Enclosed: draft of a letter in the hand of BCM marked "14-febbraio" on verso; [1919 Apr 9] 1 p.; 1919 May 11 1 p. Telegram; 1919 May 26 1 p.
    - 1919 May 28-Dec 31 Labelled by BCM: "dal 28 maggio al 31 dicem" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1919 May-Dec Ricevuto grazie... 1 p. Telegram; [1919 May-Dec] Penso sempre sempre a te... 1 p.; [1919 May-Dec] Sono venuto qui per... 2 p.; [1919 May-Dec] Sono con te con te... 3 p.; [1919 May-Dec] non temere, non devi... 2 p.; [1919 May-Dec] ho avuto delle giornate... 3 p.; [1919 May-Dec] Saro alla porta... 1 p.
    - 1919 May-Dec Saro Roma domani... 1 p. Telegram; [1919 May 29] 1 p.; [1919 May 30] 1 p.; [1919 Jun 2] 1 p.; [1919 Jun 17] no message, signature underlined once Postcard; [1919 Jun 17] no message, signature underlined twice Postcard
    - [1919 Jun 17] Penso sempre a te... 1 p.; 1919 Jun 17 1 p. Telegram; [1919 Jun 28] 2 p.; 1919 Jul 11 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Jul 24 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Jul 28 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Aug 9 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Aug 12 1 p. Telegram
    - [1919 Aug 16] 2 p. l919 Aug 16 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Aug 26 Non temere... 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Aug 26 Sempre con profonda... 1 p. Telegram; [1919 Aug 26] 1 p.; [1919 Aug 27] 1 p.; [1919 Sep 22] 1 p.
    - [1919 Sep 24] Cara, penso sempre sempre... 1 p. Cara, penso a te a te... 1 p. Two letters in one envelope; 1919 Oct 18 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Oct 28 1 p. Telegram; [1919 Oct 31] 2 p.; 1919 Nov 7 1 p. Telegram; [1919] Nov 13 1 p. Telegram
    - [1]919 Nov 28 1 p. From prison; 1919 Dec 9 1 p. Telegram; 1919 Dec 12 1 p. Telegram
    - 1920 Jan-Apr Labelled by BCM: "1 gennaio 1 luglio 1920" (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - [1920] Ti amo tanto... 1 p.; [1920] Ti prego di scusarmi... 1 p.; [l920] Ti penso sempre... 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Jan 18?] 1 p.; 1920 Jan 26 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Jan 28 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Jan 31 1 p. Telegram
    - [1920 Feb 26] 1 p.; [1920 Feb? 27] 1 p.; [1920 Feb 28] 1 p.; 1920 Mar 2 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Mar 2] 2 p.; [1920 Mar 25] 1 p.; [1920 Mar 27] Ho sete di te 1 p.; [1920 Mar 27] Penso a te... 1 p.
    - [1920 Mar 30] 1 p.; [1920] Mar? 31 Penso sempre... 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Mar 31 Prevedevo la... 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Apr 1] 1 p.; 1920 Apr 3 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Apr 6 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Apr 8] 1 p.; 1920 Apr 9 1 p. Telegram
    - 1920 Apr 13 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Apr 14 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Apr 19 1 p. Telegram
    - 1920 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1920 May 19 1 p. Telegram; 1920 May 21 1 p. Telegram; 1920 May 22 1 p. Telegram; [1920] Jun? 7 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Jun 10] 1 p.; 1920 Jun? 11 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Jun 14 1 p. Telegram
    - 1920 Jun 15 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Jun 15] 2 p.; 1920 Jun 17 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Jun 18 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Jun 21 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Jun? 23] 3 p.; [1920 Jun 25] 1 p.; 1920 Jun 26 1 p. Telegram
    - Jul 1920-Dec 1921 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1920 Jul-Dec Labelled by BCM: "1 luglio 31 dicembre 1920"
    - 1920 Aug 5 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 3 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 6 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 9 Tanti baci... 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 9 Spero tornare... 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 10 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Sep 11 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Oct 13 1 p. Telegram
    - [1920 Oct 15] 3 p. Also signed "Alberto" (Cappa); [1920 Oct 17] 1 p.; [1920 Oct 18] Penso a te a te... 2 p.; [1920 Oct 18] Penso a te oggi... 1 p.; [1920 Oct 19] 2 p.; 1920 Oct 21 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Oct 23] Ho un desiderio... 4 p.
    - [1920 Oct 23] Un lungo... 1 p.; 1920 Oct 27 1 p. Telegram; 1920 [Oct?] 30 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Nov 10] Sono in pieno lavoro... 1 p.; [1920 Nov 10] Scrivimi, tu, una... 1 p.; 1920 Nov 10 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Nov 15] Brava! Bene! 1 p.; [1920 Nov 15] ti ringrazio... 3 p.
    - 1920 Nov 17 1 p. Telegram; 1920 Nov 22 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Nov 23] 2 p.; [1920 Nov 24] 2 p.; [1920 Nov 26] Non mi piace la tua... 3 p.; [1920 Nov 26] ho bisogno di scriverti... 4 p.; 1920 Nov 27 1 p. Telegram; [1920] Dec 22 1 p. Telegram
    - [1920 Dec?] 23 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Dec 23] 2 p.; [1920 Dec 24] 2 p.; [1920] Dec 26 1 p. Telegram; [1920 Dec 27] 3 p.; 1920 Dec 29 1 p. Telegram
    - 1921 Jan-Apr Labelled by BCM "1921" (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - [1921] Ho sete sete... 1 p.; [1921] Penso sempre... 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Crema successone... 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Spero essere... 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Sarò probabilmente... 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Esposizione trionfa... 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jan?] Ti mando... 1 p.
    - 1921 Jan 2 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jan 7] Mi alzo... 1 p.; 1921 [Jan] 7 Sono a Parigi... 1 p.; [1921] Jan 7 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jan 10] 1 p.; [1921 Jan 11] 1 p.; [1921 Jan 12?] 1 p.; [1921 Jan 13] 1 p.
    - 1921 Jan 15 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jan 18] 1 p.; 1921 Jan 20 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Jan 25 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Jan 25 Si si con te... 1 p.; 1921 Jan 25 Vengo da Ginevra... 1 p.; 1921 Jan 26 2 p.
    - 1921 Jan 31 3 p.; 1921 Jan 31 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Feb 21 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Mar 16 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Mar 19 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 7? 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 8 1 p. Telegram
    - 1921 Apr 9 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 14 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 15? 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 17 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Apr 20 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Apr 21 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Apr 29] 1 p.
    - 1921 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1921 May 1 1 p. Telegram; [1921 May 5] Penso a te a te... 1 p.; [1921 May 5] Speravo avere oggi... 2 p.; 1921 May 8 1 p. Telegram; 1921 May 16 1 p. Telegram; [1921 May 17] 3 p.; [1921 May 31] 1 p.
    - [1921 Jun 6] 2 p.; [1921 Jun] Martedi 7 3 p.; [1921] Jun 7 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jun 8] 4 p.; [1921 Jun 11?] 6 p.; [1921 Jun 13] Ti scrivo sperando... 2 p.; [1921 Jun 13] La posta sembra... 1 p.; [1921 Jun 13] Forse questa lettera... 2 p.
    - [1921 Jun 14?] 3 p.; [1921 Jun 16] Vivo di te... 2 p.; [1921 Jun 16] Sempre con te... 2 p.; [1921] Jun 18 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Jun 18] 1 p.; [1921 Jun 21] 5 p.; [1921 Jun 22] Ricevo ora... 4 p.; [1921 Jun 22] Penso a te... 2 p.
    - [1921 Jun 24?] 2 p.; [1921 Jun 26] 2 p.; [1921] Jun 29 1 p.
    - 1921 Jul-Oct (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - [1921] Jul 5 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Jul 8 1 p. Telegram; [1921] Jul 21 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Sep 19] 2 p.; [1921 Sep 22] Non voglio, cara Beny... 2 p.; [1921 Sep 22] tante tante cose da fare... 2 p.; [1921 Sep 22] ricevo ora la tua... 4 p.
    - [1921 Sep 22] Scrivimi se stai bene... 2 p.; [1921 Sep 23] 1 p.; 1921 [Sep?] 27 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Oct 1?] 4 p. AL; 1921 Oct 2 Ti penso... 1 p. Telegram; 1921 Oct? 2 Scrivimi... 1 p.; Telegram [1921 Oct 3] 1 p.; [1921 Oct 4] 2 p.
    - 1921 [Oct?] 5 1 p. Telegram; [1921 Oct 8] 2 p.; [1921 Oct 10] 8 p.; [1921 Oct 13] 1 p.; [1921 Oct 15] 3 p.; 1921 Oct 31 Telegram
    - 1921 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - [1921][Nov?] 18 Telegram; [1921] Nov 21 Telegram; [1921 Nov? 21?] 1 p.; [1921 Nov 22] 4 p.; [1921 Nov 23?] 1 p.; [1921 Nov 24] Ti penso sempre... 1 p.; [1921 Nov 24] parto per Roma... 2 p.
    - [1921 Dec ?] 2 p.; 1921 Dec 2 Telegram; [1921 Dec 9] 2 p.; [1921 Dec 10] Con te con te sempre... 2 p.; [1921 Dec 10] ti ho scritto ieri... 2 p.; [1921 Dec 11] 2 p.; [1921 Dec 13] 4 p.; [1921 Dec 14] 2 p.
    - 1922 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - [1922 Jan 7?] Scrivimi Sabato come stai... 1 p.; [1922 Jan 7] Qui fa un freddo... 2 p.; [1922 Jan 10?] 5 p.; [1922 Jan 11] 3 p.; [1922? Feb?] Freddo atroce... 1 p.; [1922 Feb 6] Tempo atroce... 2 p.; [1922 Feb 6] Parto oggi... 1 p.
    - [1922] Feb 10 1 p.; 1922 Feb 12 Telegram; 1922 Mar 27 4 p.; [1922 Mar 28] ieri sera... 2 p.; [1922 Mar 28] Se tieni a farmi... 1 p.; [1922 Mar 29] 2 p.; [1922 Apr 4] 1 p.; 1922 Apr 5 Telegram
    - 1922 Apr 8 Ti penso sempre... Telegram; 1922 Apr 8 Spero tornare... Telegram; 1922 Apr 10 Telegram; [1922 Apr 21] 4 p.; [1922 Apr 22] 2 p.; [1922 Apr 24] 1 p.; [1922 Apr 25] 3 p.
    - 1922 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - [1922 May 22] Il pensiero di te... 4 p.; [1922 May 22] Sono stato in casa... 2 p.; [1922 May 22] Penso a te... 1 p.; [1922 May 24] 6 p.; 1922 May 26 Telegram; 1922 May 29 Telegram; [1922 May 30] dunque grande crisi... 2 p.
    - [1922 May 30] Sono con te con te 2 p.; [1922 May 31] 2 p. Enclosure: Comoedia, 1922 May 28; 1922 Jun 1 Telegram; 1922 Jun 1 5 p. Enclosure: Der Futurismus no. 1 (May 1922)
    - [1922 Jun 3?] 1 p. Enclosures: "'Le Strade del Deserto' (dal'Tamburo di fuocco' di F. T. Marinetti) Il Popolo d'Italia, 2 Jun 1922; "Teatri e concerti," Il Secolo 4 Jun [1922]; and "Fatti e figure del Giorno, Filippo Tommaso Marinetti", Il Secolo, 4 Jun [1922]
    - 1922 Jul-Oct (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - [1922 Sep 13] 4 p.; [1922 Sep 14] 2 p.; [1922 Sep 18] 5 p.; [1922 Sep 21] ieri ho visitato... 2 p.; [1922 Sep 21] Domenica a Salsomaggiore... 4 p.; [1922 Sep 21] Oggi ho visitato... 4 p.; [1922 Sep 21?] Ti penso sempre... 1 p.
    - [1922 Sep 22] 1 p.; [1922 Sep 23] 1 p.; [1922 Sep 25] 8 p.; [1922 Sep 27] 2 p.; 1922 Sep 29 Telegram; [1922 Oct 3] 3 p.
    - 1922 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1922 Nov 1 Telegram; [1922 Nov 5] 1 p.; [1922 Nov 6] 1 p.; 1922 Nov 6 Telegram; 1922 Nov 11 Telegram; [1922 Nov 17] 1 p.; [1922 Nov 18] 2 p.
    - [1922 Nov 19] 2 p.; [1922 Nov 20] 4 p.; [1922 Nov 21] 3 p.; [1922? Nov 25?] 2 p.; [1922 Nov 27?] 8 p.; [1922 Nov 28?] Sono a Lione... 2 p.; [1922 Nov 28?] Non mi scrivi nulla... 1 p.; [1922 Nov 30?] 10 p.
    - [1922 Dec l?] Parto oggi ore... 2 p.; [1922 Dec 1] Speravo trovare qui... 4 p.; [1922 Dec 4] ricevo tua lettera... 4 p.; [1922 Dec 4] Ricevo tua seconda lettera... 4 p.; [1922 Dec 5] 2 p.; [1922 Dec 7] Spero che la... 3 p.; [1922 Dec 7] Sono ancora tutto... 10 p.; [1922 Dec 8] Ieri sera tornando... 4 p.
    - [1922 Dec 8?] Parto ora per Milano... 2 p.; [1922 Dec 19?] 1 p.; [1922 Dec 27] 7 p.; 1922 Dec 29 Telegram
    - 1923 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - [1923 Jan 19] 2 p.; [1923 Jan 20?] 8 p. Enclosure: "Il Teatro Independente e la sua Novità", Il Giornale d'Italia, 1923 Jan 20; [1923 Jan 21] 1 p.; [1923 Jan 23] 2 p.; [1923 Jan 26] 2 p. Enclosures: lottery ticket (?); 2 p., in an unidentified hand, on Dr. Marzocco's treatment of distemper in puppies
    - 1923 Jan 27 Telegram; [1923 Jan 29] 3 p.; 1923 Jan 31 Telegram; 1923 Feb 21 Telegram; [1923?] Feb 25 Telegram; 1923 Mar 22 Telegram; [1923 Mar 22] 1 p. Enclosure: "Letture e Conferenze", La Vita Intellettuale a Milano, n.d.
    - [1923 Mar 23] 4 p.; [1923 Mar 26] Parto ora per Cesena... 1 p.; [1923 Mar 26] Penso sempre a te... 1 p.; 1923 Mar 26 Telegram; 1923 Apr 24 Telegram; [1923 Apr 25] 1 p.; [1923 Apr 27] 4 p. Enclosure: "Il futurismo di Sofocle" (on a speech by FTM; 25 Apr 1923) Il Giornale d'Italia, 26 Apr 1923
    - 1923 Apr 29 Telegram; 1923 Apr 30 2 p. Enclosures: 2 p. letter to FTM from Alberto (Cappa) and an article by Cappa, "Filippo Tommaso Marinetti o il pessimismo sociale d'un Ottimista individuale," Rivista di Milano, n.d., p. 200-206.
    - 1923 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 1923 May 6 Telegram; [1923 May 11] Sento il bisogno di... 2 p.; [1923 May 11] volevo partire ieri... 2 p.; 1923 May 19 Telegram; [1923 May 19] ti amo tanto tanto... 2 p.; [1923 May 19] ho ricevuto tue lettere... 5 p.; 1923 May 22 Telegram
    - [1923 May 22] dopo Mantova... 3 p.; [1923 May 22] Ieri sera prima di... 5 p.; [1923 May 22] Il mio articolo... 4 p.; [1923 May 23] Ti ho mandato... 4 p.; [1923 May 23] Come? I giorni senza... 3 p.; 1923 May 24 Telegram; [1923 May 24] Fra un ora parlerò... 2 p.; [1923 May 24] Ieri sera ultima... 4 p.
    - [1923 May 25] 3 p.; [1923 May 26] 2 p.; [1923 May 28] dopo molte riunioni... 2 p.; [1923 May 28] Penso ate con... 1 p.; [1923 May 28] Oggi seconda riunione... 3 p.; [1923 May 28] spero rivederti il... 1 p.; [1923 May 30] 4 p.; 1923 May 31 Telegram
    - [1923 Jun 3] 3 p.; 1923 Jun 4 Telegram; 1923 Jun 23 Telegram
    - Jul 1923-Dec 1926 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1923 Jul-Sep
    - [1923 Jul 14] 1 p.; 1923 Jul 17 Telegram; [1923 Jul 19] Non mi spiego... 2 p.; [1923 Jul 19] Speravo avero oggi... 1 p.; [1923 Jul 20] 2 p.; [1923 Jul 22] 4 p.; [1923 Jul 23] 11 p.
    - [1923 Jul 24] 1 p.; [1923 Jul 27] 3 p.; [1923 Jul 29] 1 p. Enclosure: letter to FTM from Carla Caillot Caiani, dated 27 Jul 1923; 1923 Jul 30 Telegram; [1923 Aug 1] 5 p.; 1923 Aug 11 Telegram; 1923 Aug 29 Telegram
    - 1923 Sep 3 Telegram; 1923 Sep 28 Telegram; 1923 Sep 28 Telegram; [1923 Sep 28] 2 p.
    - 1923 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - [1923 Oct 1] 5 p.; [1923 Oct 2] 2 p.; 1923 [Oct?] 3 Telegram; [1923 Oct 5] Ho molto lavorato... 1 p.; [1923 Oct 5] ho parlato lungamente... 2 p.; 1923 Oct 7 Telegram; [1923 Oct 8] 4 p.
    - 1923 Oct 9 Telegram; 1923 Oct 10 Telegram; [1923 Oct 11] 3 p.; [1923 Oct 13] Spero rivederti fra... 2 p.; [1923 Oct 13] Ti scrivi recentamente... 2 p.; [1923 Oct 30] ho preso a tempo... 3 p.; [1923 Oct 30] non ho visto ieri... 1 p.; 1923 Oct 30 Telegram
    - [1923 Oct 31] 2 p.; [1923 Nov 5] 1 p. Enclosure: Letter to BCM from Arturo Cappa, dated 30 Oct [1923] announcing the death of Rougena Zátkova.; [1923 Nov 6] ieri mattina ho trovato... 3 p.; [1923 Nov 6] Ieri sera Alberto è... 2 p.; [1923 Nov 7] ricevo ora da Milano... 3 p.; [1923 Nov 7] Ti mando tanti... 1 p.
    - [1923 Nov 9] Grazie Grazie per... 3 p.; [1923 Nov 9] Ho ricevuto ora... 2 p.; [1923 Nov 10] 1 p.; 1923 Nov 12 Telegram; 1923 Dec 6 Telegram; [1923?] Dec 17 Telegram
    - 1924 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1924 Jan 8 Lavoro molto... Telegram; 1924 Jan 8 Tanti baci... Telegram; [1924 Jan 9] 2 p.; 1924 Jan 9 Telegram; [1924 Jan 11] 2 p.; 1924 Jan 12 Telegram; 1924 Jan 13 Telegram
    - 1924 Jan 16 pagherò notaio... Telegram; 1924 Jan 16 Spero vederti... Telegram; [1924 Jan 17] 1 p. Enclosure: "La Bella Battaglia Futurista Data Ieri Sera a Milano" by Ettore Romagnoli, La Vita [intellettuale?] a Napoli, v. 3, no. 11 (2?), n.d.; 1924 Jan 17 Telegram; [1924 Jan 22] 2 p.
    - [1924 Jan 23] 1 p.; 1924 Jan 23 Telegram; [1924 Jan 26] Ieri a Padova... 2 p.; [1924 Jan 26] Sono a Venezia... 2 p.; 1924 Jan 26 Telegram; 1924 Jan 29 Telegram; 1924 Feb 22 Telegram; [1924 Feb 23] Nel golfo tutti... 2 p.
    - [1924 Feb 23] Del Guzzo era... 2 p.; 1924 Feb 24 Telegram; [1924 Feb 27] 3 p.; [1924 Feb 28] 4 p.; [1924 Feb 29] 4 p.; [1924 Mar 1] 2 p.; [1924 Mar 3] 1 p.
    - [1924 Mar 4] 3 p. Enclosure: clipping (from Il [Giornale d'Italia] ?, 4 Mar 1923? or 1924?), containing part of four articles; [1924 Mar 7] 6 p.; 1924 Mar 13 Telegram; [1924 Mar 21] ti spedisco le due... 2 p.; [1924 Mar 21] ho dimenticato di... 1 p. Enclosure: TLS from Franco Campitelli to FTM, 17 Mar 1924
    - [1924 Mar 24] Ti penso sempre... 2 p.; [1924 Mar 24] Ieri sera esposizione... 2 p.; [1924 Mar? 26] 1 p.; 1924 Mar 28 Telegram
    - 1924 Apr-Dec (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 1924 Apr 1 Telegram; [1924 Apr 4] 3 p.; 1924 Apr 4 Telegram; [1924 Apr 23] la conferenza è stata... 2 p.; [1924 Apr 23] Ricevo ora la tua lettera... 1 p.; 1924 Apr 28 Telegram; 1924 Apr 29 Telegram
    - 1924 Apr 30 Spero partire domani... Telegram; 1924 Apr 30 Spero vederti domani... Telegram; 1924 May 11 Telegram; 1924 May 15 Telegram; 1924 May 16 Telegram; 1924 May 17 Telegram; 1924 May 18 Telegram; 1924 May 19 Telegram
    - 1924 Oct 26 Telegram; 1924 Nov 5 Telegram; 1924 Nov 6 Telegram; 1924 Nov 9 Telegram; 1924 Nov 10 Telegram; 1924 Nov 11 Telegram; 1924 Nov 12 Telegram
    - 1924 Nov 13 Telegram; 1924 Nov 15 Identical telegrams, one numbered Telegram 1924 Nov 15 103 and the other numbered 104 Telegram
    - 1925 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - 1925 Jan 3 4 p.; [1925 Jan 5] 2 p.; [1925 Jan 9] 4 p.; [1925 Jan 12] 2 p.; [1925 Jan 14] 2 p.; [1925 Feb 25] 1 p.; [1925 Feb 27] 3 p.; [1925 Mar 30] penso a te... 1 p.
    - [1925 Mar 30] Il congresso è finito... 3 p.; [1925 Apr 2?] 2 p.; [1925 Apr 3] 5 p.; [1925 Sep 25] 2 p.; 1925 Sep 28 Telegram; 1925 Oct 27 Ricordati baci... Telegram; 1925 Oct 27 Ricordati tanti baci... Telegram; [1925 Oct 27] 2 p.
    - [1925? Oct 28] 2 p.; 1925 Oct 31 Telegram; [1925 Dec 18] 2 p.; [1925 Dec 21] 3 p.; [1925 Dec 22] 4 p.; 1925 Dec 27 Telegram
    - 1926 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - [1926 Jan 12?] 2 p.; [1926 Jan 14] 3 p.; [1926 Jan 15] partirò-spero-domani... 1 p.; [1926 Jan 15] nevica nevica nevica!... 1 p.; 1926 Jan 17 Telegram; [1926 Jan 18] 1 p.; [1926 Jan 27] 4 p.; [1926 Jan 29] 2 p.
    - [1926 Jan 30] 2 p.; [1926 Feb 1] 3 p.; [1926 Feb 15] 2 p. Enclosures: "L'on. Mussolini inaugura a Milano la Mostra del 'Novecento italiano'", Corriere della Sera, 15 Feb 1926; "Il Gruppo Futurista italiano alla XV Biennale di Venezia, La Mostra annunziata da F. T. Marinetti in un'intervista alla 'Gazzetta di Venezia'", n.d., in unidentified newspaper
    - 1926 Feb 15 Telegram; [1926 Feb 17] Oggi ho parlato... 4 p.; [1926 Feb 17] Oggi ho ricevuto... 6 p.; [1926 Feb 25] 2 p.; [1926 Sep 13] 1 p.; [1926 Sep 14] 1 p.; 1926 Nov 4 Telegram; 1926 Nov 6 Telegram
    - 1926 Nov 9 Telegram; [1926? Nov? 12] 2 p.; 1926 Nov 17 Telegram; 1926 Nov 19 Telegram
    - Jan 1927-Apr 1928 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - 1927 Jan-Apr
    - [1927 Jan 16] 4 p.; [1927 Jan 17] 4 p.; [1927 Jan 18] 4 p.; [1927 Jan 19] 4 p.; [1927 Jan 20] 4 p.; [1927 Jan 21] 2 p. Enclosure: "F. T. Marinetti inaugura alla Casa del Fascio la Mostra di Pittura futurista", Il Resto del Carlino (Bologna), 21 Jan 1927.
    - [1927 Jan 23] tuoi quadri in perfetto... 4 p.; [1927 Jan 23] spero leggere la mia... 2 p. Enclosure: ALS from Maria Russolo to FTM, 17 Jan 1927; [1927 Jan 25] 3 p.; [1927 Jan 26] 4 p.; [1927 Mar 16] 10 p.; [1927 Mar 17] 4 p.